Well if a person has type one Diabetes then the main focus is for them to eat enough calories and carbohydrates to maintain their weight.
And so we teach people with type on Diabetes to count their carbohydrates, but not necessarily to restrict carbohydrates.
And sometimes people with type one get confused because they see a lot of messages in the media about cutting carbohydrates and actually that would cause them to lose too much weight.
On the other hand, someone with type two Diabetes generally is overweight and so they need to cut carbohydrates as well as the calories in their diets.
So generally when someone has type two Diabetes we try to help them reduce the total calorie intake.
And that includes calories from all foods and so portions are going to be smaller particularly are foods that are high in fat and carbohydrate.
In general we try to encourage people with type two Diabetes to increase their intake of vegetables that are low in sugar and fat.
And those are your broccoli, green beans, cauliflower, onions, lettuce, salad type greens, all of those vegetables that have a lot of fiber in them fill you up without giving you too much energy.
And so the big focus for somebody who has type two Diabetes is to fill half of their plate at dinner time with those that we call free foods.
They don't even have to portion them out.
And then a fourth of their plate with the foods that are high in carbohydrates like potatoes, rice, corn, dry beans, peas and noodles and then a fourth of the plate with their meat.
And when they eat that way they naturally reduce calories often without even having to measure their portions out.
So that's kind of the first step is to really get people to consume a lot more of those vegetables that are high fiber, high water content and very low on carbohydrates.